Hello everyone, I'm Pasquale Perrotta and this is the Module 2 of Diagnosis topic.
There will be three modules, the first one already available for the Diagnosis introduction,
the second one which is related to default management, and the third one which will be
a walkthrough of the UDS to understand how to read it, how to use it, and things like this.
But in the Module 2, we will work exactly for default management.
In particular, we will understand what is the status of the DTC,
analyzing the behavior of each of these eight bits.
The introduction that I gave for the Diagnosis is very general to make you aware
what is the Diagnosis, why do we use the UDS, why it is important to use it,
and things like this. But that was pretty an introductory lesson,
and not being very practical, being quite, let's say, far from the practical use of the UDS.
So the intention of these two further modules is to make you closer to the concrete activities
that you are going to do once you work for a client.
And these will be very, very, very helpful for whatever activities you are going to do,
which is going to be validation, verification, hardware-in-the-loop configuration, everything.
So this will come in handy every time.
Of course, in the slides and also in the norms that you will get, there are definitions.
So everything that I'm going to say is reported already in the norms.
So this lesson is a way to make things easier or to raise in you doubts about you understood.
But anyway, everything is already reported and present in the slides and the norms
for other presentations and things like this.
So you have the references in case of problems.
I please refer to your references.
So here there is a definition and most of all some names.
But I would like to use, as always, a tool that for me is very helpful, which is paint.
I already prepared a couple of things that could be helpful.
But here I would just like to mention two additional things.
So as we said probably in the previous module, or if not, I'm going to tell you now.
Every time we refer to a diagnostic trouble code, the DTC, we need three bytes to refer to it.
So the identification number for the specific diagnostic trouble code is based on three bytes.
Okay, so we will have something like this.
I write it here, you know, in a small character and dimension.
So we will have, I don't know, I'm just inventing, you know, a possible diagnostic trouble code
that could be, I don't know, 01, 22, 92, for example.
Okay.
Okay, we can make it even a bit bigger.
So as you see here, so I already write something, then we will understand what is that.
So let's put, let's make it be even bigger.
Okay.
So as I was saying the identification, so the ID of the diagnostic trouble code is based on
three bytes and I'm going to show you them.
So this is the first byte, this is the second byte, and this is the third byte.
Okay.
But every time we ask to the electronic control unit the list of errors that the electronic
control unit has stored inside it, and we will see how to do that.
Okay.
So probably this module or in the next module, we see how to do actually concrete way this
request.
We will always see and realize that the echo will reply always at least with four bytes.
Okay.
If there is an error present in this case.
So where three bytes are related to the identification number of diagnostic trouble code.
So let's say this is the first, this is the second, and this is the third.
But then we will also have the fourth byte.
This fourth byte is the status of DTC we are referring to.
Okay.
So this 8f that you see is, you know, a combination of 8 bit.
And according to the values of this 8 bit, we will have a specific value.
8f is an hexadecimal.
So according to the bit, the value of the bits that we will have here, we will have a
specific value of this 8f.
So please remember, we will see how to ask to the electronic control unit the list of
errors, for example.
But just keep in mind, for starters, that the diagnostic, every diagnostic trouble code is
expressed with three bytes.
And then, and this is a statical, I mean, it's a static means it's just an identification
number.
Okay.
Like, I don't know the ID of a can frame.
That is an ID and it's a static.
So this is not, this does not change.
What actually changed is the fourth byte because the fourth byte is the representation
of the actual status of the DTC.
Please guys, as always, do not learn things by earth.
So status of DTC is not just a name or a, you know, funny combination of words that someone
in the past decide to use.
Status of DTC actually means the status of the diagnostic trouble code.
Always refer to the concrete things.
Okay.
Concrete examples.
Let's always think about we are having a problem with our car and we are driving the
car on the highway.
So I already did this example in the past module.
Okay.
And what it really, what really matters is to understand what is the problem, make sure
that the car and so the software behaves properly so that everything is safe.
We can preserve the safety of the drivers, the system and all the things that we have
said.
Okay.
But once we, you know, everything is safe and, you know, all the safety part is achieved,
then it's very important for us to understand what is the status of the error.
This is from the high level point of view, but this is also important during the development
phase.
If you're performing some tests that require that the error memory is clean and you have
no errors stored.
And then you have an error always present inside, or you have an error generally in your electronic
control unit.
The first step is to understand.
Okay.
The error of error is it.
I have three bytes telling me which is the identification number.
So I can actually refer and understand what is this error.
And then looking at the fourth byte, I can see, okay, just analyzing the value of this eight
bit, I can understand if the error is present, if the error is not present.
If the error was present in the previous monitoring cycle, if it was present two monitoring cycles
ago, if it's just stored, if there is a lump on.
So these are all information that we can retrieve just looking at this fourth byte.
Okay.
So this is extremely important.
I've mentioned something that might sound new for you, which is the monitoring cycle,
but we will go through it while explaining this because we will have basically three definitions
that we are going to give today.
So one, let's make it a bit smaller.
One is the monitoring cycle.
One is the driving, oops, driving cycle.
And another one is the warm up cycle.
So we will have three definitions.
Okay.
For starters, let's, of course, these definitions in a way are reported on the norms.
So, once again, you don't have to remember everything by earth.
You just have to know, you know, where to look at, in this case, to the norm, or, you
know, just have the material to study and to read so that you know the definition of this
kind of stuff.
Please do not just study by earth.
Try to understand from the physical point of view what does it mean, all of this stuff.
So, to start with, we will define the monitoring cycle, a cycle that goes from the K off, sorry,
from the K on to K off.
Okay.
Monitoring cycle.
Once again, let's analyze the word cycle.
So it's a cycle.
Okay.
We are monitoring a period of something, but monitoring what?
Once again, here.
Okay.
I can even type it here.
Just to make things even clearer.
We are talking about a, here, the status of DTC.
Okay.
Please always remember what we are talking about.
Status of DTC.
So what are we monitoring in this cycle?
The status of the DTC.
Okay.
The two things are interconnected.
They are connected together.
Okay.
So monitoring cycle.
This is a cycle where we monitor the status of the DTC.
And then we have the driving cycle.
The driving cycle is basically a monitoring cycle with an additional condition, which is
turning the engine on.
Okay.
So we will have the conditions that we already told, I already told you before, which is
monitoring a cycle plus engine on.
So you can understand that also the warmup cycle is still a cycle, but it contains more
than one condition or two conditions.
So it contains the condition of the monitoring cycle.
So K on to K off.
It contains the condition of the driving cycle.
So you have to turn on the engine, but there are also additional conditions.
Why I'm generic.
I'm generic because it depends on the kind of car you're working with.
For example, for the internal combustion engine, there could be specific conditions like to turn
the engine on and having a specific delta temperature in the refrigerant liquid of the, yeah.
Sorry.
The temperature of the water of the engine.
There must, there must be a delta temperature of 25, 22 or 22.5 degrees.
But actually I don't remember exactly, but it's written in the norm.
So, okay.
As I said to you before, you don't remember, no problem.
You just read the norm.
That's not a problem at all.
And this is for the internal combustion engine, but there are different conditions for the hybrid,
the hybrid propulsion systems, and even more different from the electric propulsion systems.
Like there is a condition on time.
You have to stay in Kayon for a specific amount of time.
You have to drive the car with the speed faster than 30 kilometers per hour for a specific amount of time.
So it's a more restrictive condition.
So while we move down here in this small scheme, we are just adding conditions.
Okay.
So starting from the monitoring cycle, which is the, let's say the easiest one to get, getting
to the warmup cycle where actually we have a more strict, let's say conditions.
And there is a specific reason for it.
So we will understand why do we have these three different scenarios and give you some details
about it.
Okay.
So, okay, it's right.
Please keep, while you watch this video, it might be helpful to have this scheme in front
and ahead of you.
Okay.
So it's easier to understand names, but they're real, real, very, very simple.
So let's try to do without the support of the scheme, but would be helpful for you to have it.
So let's start to read from right-hand side to the left side.
Okay.
Bit zero, test field.
So here we are in the hypothesis that the diagnostic trouble code in question, which is 01-22-92,
is monitored every, I don't know, 10, every 100 milliseconds.
Okay.
So this means that remembering everything that we have said in the past module, which is,
you know, all the definition of the diagnosis, the fact that the Diego must be able to retrieve signals, compare signals,
process signals in a specific amount of time with a specific cycle time, stuff like this.
Here we work in the hypothesis that every 10 milliseconds, sorry, 100 milliseconds, we will have a check on the status of DTC.
Nice.
This is very important for many reasons.
First of all, because according to the kind of electronic control unit you will work with, you will find that most of the DTCs are with a specific cycle time check.
So it means that every, I don't know, 10 milliseconds, 50 milliseconds, 100 milliseconds, the status of DTC is checked.
This is mostly true for powertrain electronic control unit because they manage critical components like the accelerator pedal,
like the water temperature, battery temperature, for example, and stuff like this.
But if we move to other electronic control units, like, I don't know, I don't know, headlights or the cluster or the LTM radio or whatever,
most of the time the check on the DTC is not cyclical but is on event.
So you must do something, for example, pressing a button to control the status of a specific DTC.
Okay.
Or to test that everything is okay for that DTC.
Here, for the sake of this explanation, we will say that the check is cyclical.
So every 100 milliseconds, there's going to be a check on the status of this DTC.
So let's consider that this DTC, the 0122.92, is an open load on, I don't know, a specific component.
Okay.
So basically, the fault is I have an open load.
So basically, I don't know, a wire that has been cut.
And whenever the load is open, so there is a missing pin or basically the wire is cut, then the fault is injected.
So I have actually an electrical problem.
So let's consider this example and let's go through these bits.
Bit 0 is the test fail.
It's called test fail.
So it says in a very clear way, also from the definition, that this bit will be 0 if the last test executed was okay.
This means that I'm in the conditions to perform a check on the status of the DTC.
This check has been done, and the last time this check has been done, if it's 0, then it means that the test was okay.
So there were no problems encountered.
If there was, there is a problem, then, so the test fails, then this bit goes to 1.
Okay.
So please remember, this is the result of the last test executed.
Why I'm stressing out this concept?
Because there are two main things to be said about it.
First of all, there must be the conditions to perform a test.
So I'm saying, I'm putting myself in the easy example of 100 milliseconds cycle time.
Okay.
So in this case, I know that every 100 milliseconds, a test is going to happen.
In the hypothesis that this is the only thing that we need, just the elapsing of time.
It's not like this, because to perform a test, the electronic control unit must be supplied.
The software should support the check of the retrieving of these signals.
The hardware has to be able to perform this kind of test.
So there are also other preconditions, which now I'm not mentioning.
For now, let's just consider that the only condition that we need is that we need 100 milliseconds to elapse,
so that the echo has all the time to perform the checks related to this error.
Okay.
In this case, we already have all the preconditions.
But in the example of, as I was mentioning before, specific, let's say, minor electronic control units that do not have this kind of logic,
but I have a logic on event, so I have to do something, the test will be executed every time, for example, I push a button.
Because the only way to check if the circuit behind the button is working or not is by pressing the button, trying to actuate it, basically.
So in that case, I will not have a test every 100 milliseconds, but I will have a test every time I push the button.
Okay.
So this is very different.
So keep in mind that here we are in the hypothesis of a cycle time on the status of the DTC check.
Okay.
Every 100 milliseconds, a check happens, no other word.
It's not that easy, but for the sake of the explanation, yeah, now it's that easy.
Okay.
This means that if we have a, let's say, a check every 100 milliseconds, let's say that here, here,
the monitoring cycle starts.
Okay.
So here we have an event of KON.
So once we have the KON, we are starting a monitoring cycle.
Okay.
This means that, okay, now I'll stretch a bit timeline, but let's consider that here, oops, sorry, here, 100 milliseconds are elapsed.
So this is, this is 100 milliseconds.
Okay.
Let's use the text box 100, oops, 100 milliseconds.
Great.
Considering that this is 100 milliseconds, then as I was saying, I will stretch the timeline because
I need this specific scheme for, to explain the bit six, but anyway, it means that here,
after 100 milliseconds, I will have the first test executed.
So if here, after 100 milliseconds, the test fails, then this bit goes to one.
If the test is okay, the bit stays to zero.
But I, I said before that this is the, the, the result of the last test executed.
So it means that after 100 milliseconds, I have an update and it updates to zero to one,
according to, if you have or not the error, but then there will be one other 100 milliseconds.
Then another 100 milliseconds, 100, 100, 100, 100, and so on.
This means that every time, every time, guys, please remember this.
Every time I have 100 milliseconds elapse, I have an update here, here, here, here, here,
here, here, here, here, and here.
Okay.
So every time I, if the condition is just that the check is done every 100 milliseconds, then
every 100 milliseconds, I will have an update of this bit.
So if we consider that here, the error is present, here, this will be one.
Maybe here, I still have the problem.
It's one, one, one.
Then the error disappears.
So I will have zero, zero, zero, zero, zero, zero, for example.
Okay.
So please remember, this is the result of the last test executed.
So if I execute test every 100 milliseconds, it means that that bit is updated every 100 milliseconds.
Guys, this is very important because when you will work with the diagnostic tools or simply,
you will look for the logs in Chem, most of the time, you will see a static value.
Okay.
For example, 8f.
So for you, it will mean that that bit is always to one.
Then we see why I'm saying that with 8f, the bit zero is one.
You will see always as it doesn't one.
But in reality, if you, in the low level, let's say from the hardware point of view,
and also from the software point of view, that bit is always updated every 100 milliseconds in this case.
Okay.
Even if you see that it's a stacked one, it's not stacked one, because that is updated at every test that is executed.
In this case, the test is executed every 100 milliseconds.
It means every 100 milliseconds, we will have the update of the bit zero.
Okay.
Nice.
So now let's consider that we have this bit two one, for example.
Okay.
Because the test is failing.
Let's consider the last time we have the test here fails.
Okay.
So the test fails here.
And then this one.
Great.
Bit one test failed this monitoring cycle.
So now we start to use this idea, the idea of the monitoring cycle from K on to K off.
The bit one, yeah, let's see the logic behind the bit one being zero or one.
So if at least one test is executed and that test fails in that monitoring cycle, so from a K on to a K off,
that bit will go to one.
So if I have at least one test failed in this monitoring cycle, then this bit will go to one.
If I have no error test failed in this monitoring cycle, then that bit goes to zero.
Okay.
So in this case, if we consider here that we have had a K on event, and then where there is this green bar,
we have a K off event, and then a K on to start a new monitoring cycle.
Here we have a monitoring cycle, you know, because we have had a K on and we have had a K off.
So this is a monitoring cycle.
According to the definition that I gave you, and according to the definition that UDS gives you,
as we see here, we have plenty of tests failed here.
So even with one test failed, so let's consider that everything here is okay,
but we have this first error, this first check failing, then we will have one test executed,
at least one test executed failed, so this means that we will, the bit one will go to one,
because we will, we would have one test failed in this monitoring cycle.
Okay.
So once you have a test failed, that bit goes to one and stays to one,
because we already have one test failed in this monitoring cycle, so it stays to one,
and that bit is not updated anymore until we move to the next monitoring cycle.
Okay.
So once I have the error here, it means that the bit one goes to one and stays to one until the end of the monitoring cycle.
So it's not updated like the bit zero every 100 milliseconds.
No, once I have at least one test failed in this monitoring cycle,
then the bit goes to one and stays to one.
Okay.
Guys, please remember, it's extremely important to remember,
that it's not enough just to do K-ON and K-OFF to perform a monitoring cycle.
The monitoring cycle expects also a test to be executed.
Okay.
So if you are in this case, okay, you have a test every 100 milliseconds,
so you make sure that at least 100 milliseconds elapsed so that you know that the test has been executed,
and we are okay.
So we can know if a test is failed or is passed.
But if I'm in the case of a DTC that requires an action, and I do not perform the action,
so I do not press a button, for example, it means that in that monitoring cycle, I'm not performing a test.
So for the purpose of the status of DTC and everything we are going to see,
that monitoring cycle does not count because we don't know if the test failed or the test passed
because we didn't perform the test.
Okay.
Please be very careful on all the conditions needed to perform the test.
In this case, we are considering as an hypothesis that the only condition is that the echo takes 100 milliseconds
to perform these tests, and that's it.
But there might be further conditions to make the DTC check happening.
Okay.
So please always keep in mind.
Bit 2 should be the pending DTC, if I will remember.
Yes, pending DTC.
The pending DTC is the same as the bit 1, but bit 1 considers just one monitoring cycle.
The bit 2 considers two monitoring cycles.
Okay.
So the bit 2 says, goes to 1 if we have at least one test failed in this monitoring cycle or in the previous monitoring cycle.
So let's say we are here, the bit 2 checks that we have, if we have a test executed and failed here or here.
Okay.
So if we have an error in this monitoring cycle or in the previous monitoring cycle, like in this case,
because as we have seen here, it is the demonstration.
In the first monitoring cycle, we have plenty of tests failed.
This bit goes to 1.
So it's the same thing of the bit 1, but considers not just one monitoring cycle, but considers two monitoring cycles.
So I hope this is clear.
Of course, I suggest you to listen to this topic many times if you need to control the norm, everything.
Okay.
So now in the example that I'm doing, I'm considering that the final status that we will get is ATEF.
Then I will explain what is that, but let's move step by step.
So we have, we have called the test failed, which is the, a bit that gives me the result of the last test executed.
So in this case, every test is executed every 100 milliseconds.
It means that that bit is updated every 100 milliseconds.
Then we have the bit 1, test failed this monitoring cycle.
It means that if a test is failed, at least one test failed in this monitoring cycle, then this bit goes to 1.
Bit 2 pending DTC is the same.
So if we have two, if we have at least one test executed and failed in this monitoring cycle or in the previous monitoring cycle, then this bit goes to 1.
Okay.
Now we're ready to move to the bit 3.
The bit 3 is a stored DTC.
So this is easy because this bit goes to 1 if the error code, so the diagnostic trouble code, is saved inside the electronic control unit physical memory.
Okay.
So if the error is saved inside the electronic control unit memory, then this bit is 1.
In this case, we are considering that we are having problems and as soon as a test, let's say, as soon as a test fails or, yeah.
Yeah.
Let's see.
Every time, if the, at least one error, the one test fails, then the error is stored inside the electronic control unit and the bit 3 will go to 1.
Okay.
Now, okay, so let's move on.
Bit 4 and bit 5, they are not used in most of the applications, specifically for the EMEA market.
So European, African, and stuff like this.
So this bit, quite likely you will see them as a stock.
Okay.
So they could be both 0, 0, 0, or they could be 1, 1, 1, 0, or 0, 1.
Whatever.
Most of the time they are stuck.
Why?
Because they refer to a specific maneuver of clearing their memory using the error code.
Or memory using a specific service feature.
But this is not used in the EMEA market.
So most of the time you will see this bit stuck to 0.
Since this is not a rule, I mean, these are two bits that are expected in the status of the DTC.
When you start working on a specific activity, in case you were working with diagnosis or whenever you face the diagnosis, make sure to ask what is the behavior of bit 4 and bit 5.
Ask the question, are these bits used or not?
If not, which is the value they are stuck to?
Because in my experience, they have always been 0, 0.
But I have also seen 1, 1 or 1, 0, 0, 1, all kinds of combinations, really.
So whenever you start, just ask if these bits are used and if they are not used, then which is the value they are stuck to?
Of course, in case you need the behavior of bit 4 and bit 5, everything is explained in the norm and also in the slides.
So you will have support about it.
But for now, let's consider the easiest example where these bits are not used.
So we will pretend they are stuck to 0, okay?
So we consider that they are both 0 here.
So these other combinations can be erased.
Bit 6, okay, now we arrive at the situation where I needed this timeline bit stretched.
So let's consider the example of, you know, let's go back to the bit 0.
We have said that the bit 0 is updated with the last test executed on this DTC.
And that to perform a test, we need at least 100 milliseconds.
So every 100 milliseconds, a test is executed.
Okay, so we have a clear idea of what happens from here on, okay?
Because we have here 100 milliseconds.
We have the result of the first test.
We know that this has failed.
And then we put this bit for specifically at this time to 1.
Okay, great.
But what happens here?
We didn't see anything of what happens between the KON to the execution of the first test.
Here, in this 100 milliseconds, basically the electronic control unit is retrieving the signals,
is comparing them, is processing them, is trying to understand if the problem is present or not.
So, how can we understand it?
So, the only way we have to understand that a test is in execution is using the bit 6.
Bit 6 is called test not completed this monitoring cycle.
All right, so once again, the name is quite self-explanatory, okay?
So, now I will pretend that we are in these 100 milliseconds.
So, while I'm in these 100 milliseconds, it means that I'm still waiting for the first test to be executed.
So, I don't have the information about the bit 0 because I don't know the result of the last test executed in this monitoring cycle, okay?
So, the bit 0 will stay to the value of the last test executed.
That probably was, you know, before this KON, okay?
In another monitoring cycle that we do not see here, okay?
So, if the test was okay, then the bit 0 is 0.
If the test failed, then it was 1, okay?
As clear, as simple as that.
But we don't have the information, for example, on bit 1 because I don't know if an error is present or not in this monitoring cycle
because in this monitoring cycle, I have no test executed, okay?
So, in case I request the status of the DTC or simply I'm just reading the KON while I'm performing the KON
and after I've performed the KON and I'm in these 100 milliseconds, the bit 6 will stay to 1 for this full period.
Because in this full period, I have not test, not completed this monitoring cycle.
It means I don't know what is the status.
I'm still performing a test.
I'm still performing the first test.
So, until the first test is executed in this monitoring cycle, this bit will go to 1.
It means that the bit 6 here, the bit 6 is 1 for these 100 milliseconds.
As soon as the first test is executed, the bit 6 goes to 0 because one test has been executed.
Then, if it's okay, then it means that bit 0 will go to 0.
If it's not okay, the bit 0 will go to 1.
And according to these values, the bit 1 will evolve as well.
The bit 2 will evolve as well.
The bit 3 will evolve as well.
And stuff like this.
So, it is very important to understand that in this first moment from the KON
where we start the monitoring cycle and we don't have at least one test executed,
the bit 6 will stay to 1 because it will tell the user,
okay, look, I'm performing the test, but I'm not done yet.
I'm still performing the first test.
So, I don't have a clear picture of this monitoring cycle what is happening.
Right after the 100 milliseconds, in this case, we will have a first test
and the bit 6 will go to 0.
Okay.
So, basically, the bit 6 just will tell us if at least one test has been executed
in this monitoring cycle.
And if one test has been executed in this monitoring cycle,
then the bit 6 is 0 because it means, okay, we already have done one test
and we are done.
But if we are in this first 100 milliseconds where we have no tests executed,
then the bit 6 will stay to 1 until we execute the first test.
But for what we are saying now, this can be considered as 0.
bit 7 is the easiest one because the bit 7 goes to 1 in case there is the need of a lamp.
Okay.
So, if we need to turn on a warning indicator, a malfunctioning indicator lamp, the meal lamp,
for example, the bit 7 will go to 1.
It means the echo is requesting to turn on a lamp.
Okay.
Malfunctioning indication lamp.
Be careful.
This is a request done, for example, by the powertrain electronic control unit to the electronic control unit that actually manages the lamps.
For example, if we are having a problem on the accelerator pedal, it's not the powertrain electronic control unit that manages directly the lamp.
Okay.
The lamp will be managed by the APC, the cluster.
So, this 7 bit that goes to 1 is just a request to turn on a lamp.
And then another echo will receive this information over can and will turn on the lamp.
So, now we have a full picture of a potential example of a status of DTC.
But here I see just a string of bits.
Values of 0, 1, 1, 0, 1, 1, 1, 1, 0, 0, 0, 1.
Okay.
So, how do we get to this 8th half?
So, this is a very easy operation of translation, basically.
So, we start from the assumption that you can find everywhere on internet that we have this kind of association between physical values and hexadecimal values.
So, if we, 1 in a physical value is 1 in hexadecimal, 2 is 2, 3 is 3.
Well, format is completely messed up here.
So, yeah.
Let's make things a bit better.
Let's take here.
We're gonna create 4, equal 4, 5, equal 5, 6, equal 6, 7, equal 7, 8, equal 8, 9, equal 9, 10, equal A, 11, equal B, 12, equal C, 13, equal A, 11, equal B, 12, equal C, 13, equal A.
13 equal D, 14 equal E, 15 equal F.
So, keeping in mind this table, okay, where we have on the left side the decimal value and on the right side the hexadecimal value,
we can split these status of DTC in two parts here, okay, in two groups.
So, there is a very easy conversion formula to achieve what we are seeing.
So, this is, the formula is this one, two times zero times the value of the bit, okay, x, plus two times one times the value of the bit one.
Sorry for the very bad writing.
Plus two times two times the value of the second bit, plus two times three, oops, two times three times the value of the bit three.
So, what we have here, two times zero is one, one, times the value of bit zero, which is one.
So, we have one times one, one, plus two times one is two, times the value of the bit one, which is one.
So, we will have two, plus two times two is four, times the value of the bit two, which is one.
So, finally, we have four, plus two times three is eight, plus the value of the bit three, which is one, and this is eight.
Eight plus four is twelve, plus two is fourteen, plus five is fifteen.
So, finally, everything turns out in being f.
Do you see here? We have the f, it's right here, okay?
Same idea for this other sign.
So, the formula is the same, two times zero, two times one, two times two, two times three.
Here, we have all zeros.
So, these factors will just elicitate because they are times zero, so they will get cancelled.
The only factor that we will have is two times three times the value of the bit, let's say three, yeah, three of the group.
This is one, two times, two times three is eight, times one is eight.
So, the final status here will be eight.
So, the final result, if you put together the two groups, is eight f.
As you can see, guys, you just need to ask the electronic control unit the status of the DTC inside the memory or the status of the specific DTC.
And only looking at this fourth bit, this eighth F, I already know a lot of information.
I know that the last test executed failed because the bit zero is one.
So, it means that I actually, I'm having problems.
Because if the last test executed always fails, it means that I actually have the problem.
This problem is present, so, in this monitoring cycle.
So, while I'm using the car, while I'm in K-On with my car, I have a problem.
So, the car must be checked.
The problem was not present just now in this monitoring cycle.
But having the bit two to one, it means that this problem was present also in the previous monitoring cycle.
So, this is not a new problem.
This is a problem that I already had in the previous monitoring cycle.
In addition, since the test failed, I always, I also have this problem inside the electronic control unit memory.
So, yeah, the ED, this DTC is saved in the error memory because I see that the bit three is to one.
So, we're asking the electronic control unit the status of DTC.
You know, I know that I must find this ED because it is saved inside the electronic control unit.
The bit six is to zero.
So, I know that in this monitoring cycle, at least one test has been done.
So, it means that at least one, the error, the test was done and failed also because the, you know, because of all the values of the previous bits.
Bit seven is to one.
It means that I should, if I enter the car, I should expect also a lump on it.
So, just looking at this 8F and knowing how to translate the different combination of bits into hexadegimal, I have all this information.
I should expect a lump.
I know that I have a problem.
The problem is stored.
The problem was present, not just now, but also in the previous monitoring cycle.
And everything, at least one test has been done in this monitoring cycle because bit six is to zero.
So, all this stuff, I know just looking at one byte, at least the fourth byte, just looking at it, I have all this information.
So, you can understand the power of this bit and this status of the DC.
Because just looking at the byte, I have a lot, a lot, a lot of information just knowing the different combination of this bit.
So, all this video is to show you all the information going on.
My first question is maybe perhaps not just staggering into any way or not.
But yes, I who are!
And give me your last announcement for the Lethal has participated again.
So, WOE believed in the report.
I would come back just by few weeks and begin to make the report with the wong.
So, I have dubious.
I think no question is, I would look as if so.
Maybe we can sleep regularly in the days of this video.
But then the way that the system will charge the car game, or this is not really normal or something that this looks like the pain will get a copy of itself.
So, if I am doing that, I would say the first thing of the wake of time at the end of the day.
Okay, the main app on our nextICK, sort of the ep парom.
.
For example, in the example of this explanation, we were referring to a powertrain module, and usually the engine control module, let's say the echo that manages the engine, does not manage directly the lamps.
So this is just a request to the echo that will actually manage the lamp. So the echo will read the request coming from this electronic control unit, and according to the kind of request that it receives, then the echo will turn on a specific lamp.
Okay, so this is the situation, and we arrived to explain why this is defined as 8f, as remember we divide this in two parts, this is 8, and this is f.
Okay, so I can write it here, 8f. Okay, this is everything that we have explained, this is how it finished, the last module, the part one of module two.
But there are some topics to be discussed yet to close this module two.
So, okay, for me it's important to understand the actual status of the DTC, so in this case, the status of the DTC is 8f, so if you recollected the information, and all the stuff explained in the module, the first part of module two, then you will realize that now, okay, we have an active fault.
Okay, we have some kind of problem, okay, we have some kind of problem right now, but this is not on the only thing that matters to me.
Another very important thing is once I have the status of a DTC that is actually active, then I'm always, I'm also interested in, you know, clearing the error memory.
So, okay, I have a problem, but then I'm always interested in resolving the problem, you know, because most of the time when you have this kind of problems, then these will reflect on a high level point of view.
I mean, you are driving your car, you have a problem on the accelerator pedal, so it will mean that, I don't know, as we said in the example, the car will slow down, then it will turn off, then probably you can turn it on,
but then you can just drive up to, I don't know, 10 kilometers per hour, just move the car out of the street.
So, if you keep having this problem, then your car will be useless, because you still have a problem on the accelerator pedal, nothing can be done, you know, in that case, if we do not, do not take actions, and, you know, everything will stay like this.
So, there is actually the voo process of going to the past status, and that's what we are going to explain today.
Another thing to remember is that, is the hypothesis that we have over here, so I changed color, I don't know, let's take purple, so that we have a check on the status of DTC, everyone under DTC.
So, of course, I'm interested, as I was saying, to move from, I don't know, we moved from 0-0, for example, status of DTC, and now we are in 8F.
Of course, I'm interested in moving back from 8F to 0-0.
Why? In this way, when I have 0-0, again, it means that, first of all, I don't have the problem anymore.
I won't have reaction recoveries anymore, because, as I said, once you have a DTC, one of the features of a DTC is not only that I have a code inside an electronic control unit that's just a piece of metal with electrical boards and stuff,
But I actually care, I'm more, I only care, actually, that the car reacts, so that I won't get, the car won't get damaged, and most of all, we don't get hurt, and no one gets, you know, very hurt.
So, I'm really interested in this stuff, but once I'm safe, I've stopped the car safely, and I'm alive, and, you know, everything is fine,
Then, I want to come back to normal, and bring my car back to this old functionality, so this is why I want to move, again, from the status 8F to the status 0-0.
So, this implies, first of all, to remember the behavior and the definition of all these bits that we have over here,
But also, here, gets into account what we were mentioning in the module 2, part 1, and that we are explaining right now.
So, the concept of monitoring cycle, or driving cycle, or warm-up cycle.
So, let's start from the bit 0, this is the easy one.
So, as we said, the bit 0 is the last, the result of the last test executed.
So, as we, you know, considering the easy hypothesis that we made, let's draw a timeline.
Yeah, I still use a purple line, that's trying to make it as straight as possible.
Okay, this is the best I can do, and the best I can do is kind of nice, actually.
Okay, then, let's make yourself more, I don't know, whatever lines, these here, here, here, here, here, here, here, and stuff like this.
Okay, that quality, let's say, was not very, okay, so at least let's give a kind of dignity to these lines.
Okay, so let's work with this, it's not perfect, but yeah, we can work something out.
So, let's say we are in this monitoring cycle, and here, in this place, we have the status atif.
Okay, so everything starts here with atif.
Then, as you remember from the last part that you watched, and if you don't remember, please watch it back.
When we say that there is a cyclical check on this DTC, it means that every 100 milliseconds, a test is done of this DTC.
And if the test passes, then bit 0 goes to 0.
If the test is failed, because there is a problem, then this bit will stay to 1.
So, in this case, when we still have atif, it means that a test has been executed, and the test fails.
But then, there will be, you know, a delta time of 100 milliseconds.
Okay, let's consider that these are 100 milliseconds.
For some reason, let's say, for some reason, the fault was, is not present anymore.
Okay, or we can also consider, let's say, more concrete example that here, you stop the car, so you arrived, you arrived to, you know, the mechanics here, that the status is atif.
So, you brought the car there with the floor problems, the lamp is on, the car can't accelerate, you just go for 3 hours, 10 kilometers per hour, just move the car out of the way and get to the first mechanics.
So, this is everything that happened.
You stop the car.
Then, of course, you turn on the car, again, and as you know, in the first 100 milliseconds, there are no tests executed, so the bit 1 will go to 0, bit 6 will go to 1, and then we have, once again, a test.
Okay, so, then, we have other 100 milliseconds.
When you bring the car here, the mechanics, you know, I don't know, just, he does his check and realizes that the status is atif and you have an actual problem on the accelerator pedal,
let's consider that in this point, the mechanics just, you know, repair, so read the error memory, realizes that you have a problem on the accelerator pedal,
and he fixes, he or she fixes the problem on the accelerator pedal, so you won't have the problem on the potential meter anymore, okay?
So, in the strange example that the mechanic will work, staying in K-On, so it means that you, suddenly, the fault, you know, reason is not present.
So, if we have here the problem, and then, hypothetically, in this moment, mechanics just solves the problem, okay?
We will move to the red, so that it is easier.
So, here, the problem is solved.
After 100 milliseconds, a new test is executed, and this time, since the mechanic repaired everything, then we don't have the problem anymore.
But what is the change here?
Considering that we are still in this monitoring cycle, okay?
We are talking about the left side here, okay?
We are still in this monitoring cycle, okay?
So, yeah, this is not the best, you know, writing ever, but, yeah, that should be effective anyway.
So, on the left, we are still in this monitoring cycle.
After 100 milliseconds, this is 100 milliseconds, the error is not present anymore.
So, here, the only change that we have is that the last test executed passed.
So, the change is actually here, okay?
So, let's give some numbers here.
We use the Roman numbers.
This is the first, this is the second, this is the third, this is the fourth, fifth, sixth, and whatever.
If we need something, then we will use the other part of the sheet.
But, anyway, we are here in the first one.
So, the only change that I can see here is on the bit zero.
So, the bit zero changed in the first monitoring cycle, this one.
So, what will be the actual status?
We will have zero here, and then one, one, one, zero, zero, zero, one.
So, it's everything the same.
Since it's everything the same, here, we only have eight E, okay?
Why?
Because this will be one, one, one, and zero.
So, two times three times one is eight, plus four, plus two.
This is going to be 14, 14 easy, and then we have eight E, okay?
Of course, if you don't remember anything of this, if you don't really know what I'm talking about,
just please watch again, module two, and eventually also module one.
If it's not clear at all, okay?
But, just focus on the first part of module two, and this, what I'm talking about, will be very, very clear.
So, actually, here, the status at the first one, the recycle, is going to be eight E, okay?
Okay, I can even type it here, maybe, see if you're eight E.
Okay, then what happens?
The status will be always eight E here, because we, I don't know, now, 10, 100, 100, 100.
So, let's see, we have other tests.
The status will be always eight E here, because the last test executed now is passing.
So, the bit zero stays to zero.
But, since we are still in this monitoring cycle, the bit one stays to one, because we have had at least one failure, which was this one, in this monitoring cycle.
This means that bit one stays to one, bit two stays to one, bit three stays to one, and stuff like this, okay?
Then, great, perfect.
Then, we turn off the car, and turn on the car again.
So, let's consider that we moved in the second monitoring cycle.
Of course, there will be the usual 100 milliseconds, where we don't know if the error is present or not.
So, the bit six will go to one, because, you know, we are about to wait, and bit one will go to zero,
because we don't know if an error is present or not.
So, in the meanwhile, here, we will have CC as a status, okay?
Because, the bit six will go to one, bit two, sorry, bit one will go to zero.
So, we will have 1100, 1100, that is CC, because it's 12, 12 CC, okay?
Again, if you don't know what I'm talking about, just watch again the first part of module two,
and everything should be clear.
If not, just send me an email, or to automotive training, automotive.training, at sign, kinecon.it.
Anyway, so, this is, before we have the first test, so, in this first 100 milliseconds,
we will have the status is CC, but then we will have the first test.
Since we don't have the error anymore, since we don't have the error anymore,
then we will have that bit zero stays to zero, because the last test executed, this one, passed.
So, bit zero stays to zero.
But, in this monitoring cycle, we don't have any fault.
So, it means that, in this case, also the bit one goes to zero,
and this change happens in the second monitoring cycle, okay?
So, considering that we still have other checks that pass, you know, always in green,
the status of this second monitoring cycle will be 8C, okay?
Because we have zero, zero, one, one, zero, zero, zero, zero, one, okay?
We will have a separate discussion about bit seven,
and the norm and the slides will really help you about this,
because there are different, let's say, management of the lamp,
according to what kind of lamp management that DTC requires.
So, these, the slides will really help you clarify this.
But, anyway, so, we have this situation.
The bit two will stick to one,
because in the previous monitoring cycle, we still had a fault.
You see, here, this 8F is still present.
So, since the bit two says that the bit two goes to one
if an error is present in this monitoring cycle
or in the previous monitoring cycle,
considering that in both of them, we have had at least one test.
We have had at least one test in this monitoring cycle
and also in the previous one,
and in the previous one, one of the tests failed,
so, the bit two stays to one, okay?
So, the status that we have in the second monitoring cycle is HC, okay?
Great.
But, here, what happens here?
We have a monitoring cycle with no fault, okay?
Great.
Let's move on.
We will have a separate discussion also about the bit three, okay?
So, for now, let's focus on the first ones.
We don't need this anymore.
It was just an example, okay?
And this we don't need.
Okay, nice.
Third monitoring cycle, usual stop.
So, here, once again, we have 100 milliseconds,
where we don't know if there is an error or not in this monitoring cycle.
So, the status will be, once again, CC, okay?
It will be CC, but then what happens?
When we have the test here in this part,
then, here, we will have the second monitoring cycle
where no fault has been recorded
because we have had at least one test executed,
and this test executed passed
because we don't have the fault reason anymore.
So, in this case,
we will have that the bit two goes to zero as well
because we have this monitoring cycle
or the previous monitoring cycle
with no errors.
It means that the bit two can go to zero as well,
and this change happens in the third monitoring cycle, okay?
So, what we have here,
here, we have the situation
where the new status is going to be 8, 8, okay?
It's going to be 8, 8
because we have 0, 0, 0, 1, 0, 0, 0, 1, okay?
Great.
The situation stays the same.
Here, we have 8, 8, 8, 8, 8, 8, 8, 8, 8,
and we get here that we are still 8, 8.
Once again, we have a fourth monitoring cycle
where we don't know if the test is present or not.
So, we will have a status of C8
because the bit six goes to one
and everything is 1, 0, 0, 0.
And then, once we have this test that passes,
because once again,
here, we don't have the fault reason anymore,
this will become...
And, okay, here, it depends on the fault management,
lump fault management, okay?
But now, we can consider that
since we have three monitoring cycles
without an error present,
then also the lump will turn off.
You will see that there is a
mill-on-1 management,
mill-on-2 management,
mill-on-3 management,
mill-off management.
So, we have different kinds of management for lumps.
Mill-off, of course,
it means there is no need for a lump.
Mill-on-1, it means that
the lump will turn on immediately,
and turn on immediately.
Mill-on-2,
it means that the lump will turn on
after two cycles with the error.
And mill-on-3,
it means that the lump will turn on
after three cycles when we have the fault.
But then, for the...
There should be...
There is a different management
to turning off the lump.
And the turning off of lamps
usually happens after three monitoring cycles
without a fault.
Of course,
there could be some derogation to the norm.
So, that's why I'm saying
it can happen like this.
But for this kind of behavior,
refer to the norms.
And, of course,
refer to requirements of the project
you're working on.
Because there might be some derogation
to the norm,
UDS,
or simply,
you know,
just read the norm
and find out
which is the exact behavior.
But here,
we consider that
after three cycles
without an error present,
then the lump will turn off.
So, the final status here
will be 0, 8.
Okay.
Nice.
So, we have clarified everything
that led us to arrive
to this status.
0, 8.
0, 8 means that we all...
So, this is the change
that happens here
in the fourth monitoring cycle.
So, we are arriving
to the final status of 0, 8.
How can I manage these three?
This is, let's say,
the tricky one.
First of all,
here we have to do
a distinction
between two kinds of...
Okay.
Now, probably,
I will need more space.
Okay.
So, I hope this is still clear.
So, here we have
to make a distinction
between two kinds...
Let's make it bigger.
Two big kinds
of electronic control units.
Okay.
So,
I will write that here.
Let's start from
the non-power-train
power-train echo
and then we have
the power-train echo.
So,
why should I distinguish
between the two?
So,
for non-power-train
electronic control unit,
the management
of the Bith3
is just,
you know,
it's enough
for the management
of Bith3
to remember
this definition.
Okay.
Definition of the
monitoring cycle.
So,
as you remember,
and you can read this
from the slides
or from the norm,
once an error code
is saved
inside the electronic
control unit,
we have
that the error code
is stored
inside the
EEPROM
of the EECU
for 40,
for now we say,
cycles.
Okay.
So,
for the non-power-train
electronic control unit,
it might be
40 monitoring cycles.
Okay.
This is a
calibratable
value,
so the norm
suggests
it to be
40,
but it's not
mandatory.
you can
set it
as
60,
you can
set it
as
20,
you can
set it
as
800,
you know,
it's a
calibratable value,
but
it's a
common use
of this
value
is
40.
Okay.
So,
let's say,
for non-power-training
electronic control unit,
we have,
we need
monitoring cycles
without
errors
to delete
this DTC
from the error
memory.
Okay.
So,
this means
that
can we
count
this
monitoring
cycle?
This monitoring
cycle cannot
be counted
because there
is an error.
Okay.
Can we
count this?
Yes.
I'll switch
color.
We can
count this
monitoring
cycle
because there
is no
error.
we can
count this.
It's okay.
So,
here is
40.
Here is
39.
38.
Here is
37.
36.
35.
And so on.
So,
consider that
this monitoring
cycle is,
you know,
every time you
use the car.
Okay.
You turn on
the car,
for example,
or in
this case,
considering that
we are just
using the
monitoring cycle,
every time you
perform
you are
actually doing
a monitoring
cycle.
So,
every time you
turn on the
car and then
you turn off
the car,
considering that
this is on
and this is
off every
time.
So,
on,
off,
and stuff like
this.
Then it means
that every time
you use your
car,
and there is
no error,
then it's
counted as a
monitoring cycle
without fault,
so the
counter decreases.
It means that
from this point
on,
for other 37
times you will
perform monitoring
cycles,
you will still
have inside the
error memory
this DTC that
we wrote here.
So,
DTC is 01,
22,
92,
08.
You will have
this status for,
in general,
for 40 monitoring
cycles,
but from this
point on it's
going to be for
37 monitoring
cycles on.
So,
if this line
continues,
once we arrive
to the end,
so I put a
checkered flag
here to say
that we arrived
to the last
monitoring cycle,
then here the
status will be,
this is the,
let's say we
arrive to 1,
this is 1,
and then the
next one is
going to be
0,
final status
use of the
DTC.
In this case,
for non-power
training electronic
control unit,
we are saying
it's enough to
use monitoring
cycles,
so K-ON,
K-OFF,
but you can
understand,
eventually,
the risk
behind this
strategy.
If I know
about this
strategy,
that I have
a very serious
problem on my
car,
it will just
need,
we will just
need to do
40 times
K-ON,
K-OFF,
and then the
error will
disappear.
But if I have
a small issue,
like,
I don't know,
a problem on
an amplifier,
or simply one
of the lead
inside my car
is not turning
on,
for example,
and then for
some reason
I try to fix
it and I
perform 40
times K-ON,
K-OFF,
K-ON,
then the error
will disappear
and there's
going to be
no trace of
this error
inside the
electronic
control unit
for very
small problem
or for
smaller problems
this is not
a problem,
okay,
sorry for
this mix
of words,
but that's
not a huge
issue because
the issue
is very
small,
so even
though we
forced,
let's say,
the system
to delete
this error
from the
EEPROM
just doing
this 40
times K-ON,
K-OFF,
it's not a
big deal,
it doesn't
matter,
it's not a
big deal.
But when
we talk about
power train
electronic
control unit,
the power train
electronic
control unit
manages,
let's say,
very serious
problem,
and also
the problem,
the DTC
that we were
talking about
in this
example,
is the DTC
related to,
I don't know,
the accelerator
pedal,
okay,
so it is
very important
that if there's
been a problem
in the accelerator
pedal,
then there
would be
history of
this problem
inside the
EEPROM
of the
electronic
control unit.
So for the
power train
electronic
control unit
it's very
important to
keep track
of these
kind of
problems
and to
keep them
inside the
electronic
control unit
for,
let's say,
a longer
time,
but it's
not the
time,
the key
parameter
here.
The key
parameter
here is
a different
kind of
cycle,
but it's
not just
the simple
monitoring
cycle
that we
saw
before,
so it's
not going
to be
enough
to have
just a
key-off
40 times,
but there
will be
additional
conditions
to consider
a VOOL
cycle
without
an EEPROM
okay,
so for the
power train
electronic
control unit
the counter
will be
the same,
I mean,
we are still
talking about
40 cycles
without
an EEPROM,
but what
kind of
cycles?
for the
power train
electronic
control unit
we refer
to
warm-up
cycle.
In the
norms,
you should
find the
definition
of the
warm-up
cycle,
but these
days,
the
warm-up
cycle
definition
can
slightly
change
according
to the
kind of
vehicle
you're
using.
For
example,
we have
a specific
definition
for a
diesel
engine
warm-up
cycle,
we have
a specific
definition
for a
hybrid
engine
warm-up
cycle,
different
definition
of electric
vehicle,
warm-up
cycle.
So,
according to
the kind
of vehicle
that you're
using,
you might
find yourself
using
different
things,
shall we?
go ahead.
So,
the idea
is that
we cannot
use the
monitoring
cycle as
I was
describing
before just
with
maneuver
key-off
key-on,
but since
it is
very
important
to track
these
DTCs
inside the
electronic
control unit
physical
memory,
then there
are
additional
conditions.
Which
are these
additional
conditions?
So,
let's start
from the
monitoring
cycle.
The monitoring
cycle is
just
key-on,
key-off.
So,
if I do
40 times
key-on,
key-off,
then I
have,
without an
error,
I achieved
these 40
cycles without
error,
and that's it.
Let's look
at a more
severe,
let's say,
cycle,
that is the
driving cycle.
So,
the driving
cycle contains
the, let's
say,
the conditions
of the
monitoring
cycle,
so key-on,
key-off,
but there
is an
additional
condition,
that is
the engine
on.
So,
every time
you read
the driving
cycle,
it means
that it's
not enough
just to
have to
turn on
the car
with key-on
and then
key-off,
but then
you have to
perform the
key-on
turning on
the engine,
and when
you turn
off,
then the
driving
cycle
will be
done.
The
warm-up
cycle is
an even
more
severe
cycle,
because it
contains
not just
the
maneuvers
of the
monitoring
cycle,
not just
the
condition of
the driving
cycle,
but contains
also
additional
conditions.
Once again,
it depends
on the
kind of
vehicle you're
working with.
For example,
for diesel
application,
then we will
have that
the conditions
are, of course,
you have to
go in key-on,
of course,
you have to
turn on
the engine,
and there is
also a
specific
condition of
the delta
temperature of
the refrigerant
liquid of
the engine.
So,
there must be
a delta
temperature of,
if I will
remember,
22.5
degrees,
and this
delta
is valid
only if we
reach a
temperature
value of
the refrigerant
liquid higher
than 70
degrees.
For hybrid,
the application
is different.
For electric
application,
for example,
you must stay
in key-on
for a specific
amount of
time.
You have to
stay in
idle,
so with
the engine
on,
without moving
for a specific
amount of
time,
and you have
to drive
your car
with the
speed
faster than
30 kilometers
per hour
for a specific
amount of
time.
So, of course,
according to the
kind of project
you're working
on, you will
have separate
definitions and
use of this
warp-up cycle.
I know
they sound
all like
strange
rules to
be followed,
but here
there is a
very simple
idea behind
it.
If I just
use as a
condition
key-on-key-off,
it means that
even if I
don't use
the car,
just doing
40 times
key-on-key-off,
then I'm
like,
you know,
I'm kind
of joking
with the
electronic
control unit,
you know?
I'm just
making fun
of the
electronic
control unit,
pretending
that I'm
using the
car,
while actually
I'm just
doing this
stupid joke
with the
keys.
The idea
about this
warm-up cycle
is that
if I have
an error,
I will need
to keep
track
of these
errors
inside
Viprom
as long
as it
does.
So,
it means that
I have to
make sure
that for
40 times
I actually
used the
car,
the error
was not
present,
and only
after these
40 times
where I
really
used the
car,
then I
feel the
echo and
the software
will feel
confident
in deleting
the error
from the
electronic
control unit,
because it
means,
okay,
it's 40
cycles that
the car
is working
properly,
so I don't
need to
keep track
of this
error anymore.
So,
why do we
have all
these
conditions?
If we
think about
the conditions
of the
electric
vehicle,
of course,
if I use
the car,
for example,
to go out
and buy
milk,
or to
go out
and,
you know,
just going
to a
party,
disco,
to a
museum,
or whatever,
for sure,
I will have
the car
in K-ON,
for example,
because I
have to
set the
navigator,
okay,
and that's
the first
condition to
have the
car just
in K-ON
for a
specific
amount
of time,
for sure,
I will
drive,
stay
like in
standby
for a
few
seconds
with the
engine
on,
because I'm
100% sure
that on
my way
I will
find traffic
lights,
especially
if you
live in
Torino,
and that's
the second
condition,
and if I'm
using the
car,
especially
if I have
people
with me,
just to
show off
that I'm
able to
drive,
then probably
quite like
I'll
drive my
car for
a specific
amount of
time to
a speed
faster than
30 km
per hour,
so these
are all
a set of
conditions that
are all
present when
you really
use the
car,
so all
these
additional
conditions
are meant
to simulate
let's say
real driving
cycle,
and if
for 40
times I
have all
these conditions
and there
is no
fault,
then I
feel confident
that from
this 08
I can
move to
0,
okay,
so if in
all these
cycles that
I was
referring
before,
we didn't
do just
key-off,
key-on,
but also
engine-on,
then engine
install,
you know,
standby for
a specific
amount of
time,
then driving
the speed
faster than
30 km
per hour
for a
specific
amount of
time,
or I
don't know,
if you
are using
an internal
combustion
engine car,
then simply,
you know,
turning on
the engine,
keeping on
the engine
for a
specific
amount of
time,
so that
the delta
temperature
of the
refrigerant
liquid
goes
higher than
70 degrees
with a
delta of
22.5
degrees,
you know,
all these
conditions
that look
like just
a set of
roads,
actually
simulation
of a
real
case
use of
the
car,
and
if we
consider
that
in all
these
monitoring
cycles,
all these
conditions
are met,
then we
can
consider
a
discount
decreasing
until
we get
to zero
and
this
status,
you know,
the status
of the
DTC
will become
zero,
and
the DTC
is actually
deleted
from the
electronic
control unit.
I hope
this is
clear,
otherwise
the nice
exercise to
be done
is using
one of the
facilities
that we
have in
the company
or even
one of the
facilities
you're using
on your
work and
just trying
to perform
this exercise.
So you
actually set
the DTC,
so, you know,
perform the
fault condition,
I don't know,
an open load
on a
can
network,
for example,
or on a
sensor,
whatever,
you open
load,
you see
that there
is a
DTC,
you will
probably read
the status
byte,
can be
8F,
0F,
whatever,
and then you
check for
this specific
DTC if there
is a
monitoring cycle
to be done
or a
warm-up cycle
to be done,
and while you
are working
on it,
you perform
K-off,
K-on
without the
error,
and you
see how
the status
byte evolves
to become
from 8F
or 0F
to 0,
0,
using the
monitoring cycle
or the
warm-up cycle.
If you read
through the
slides,
there is
a specific
diagnostic
service to
retrieve
the amount
of
cycles
left
to get
to the
status
0,
and this
can be
retrieved
with
the
service
1906.
So,
as you
remember,
19 is
the service,
02 is
the
subservice
to read
the error
memory.
So,
we can
even write
that here.
So,
we have
error
memory
snapshot
extended data
record.
extended
data
record.
You can read
all the information
in the chapter
of the UDS
norm about
1906.
This is the
usual service
19,
the subservice
06,
that is used
to read the
extended data
record,
which gives you
a few information.
Among this
information,
one of the information
is the amount
of cycles
needed
to
clear
the error
from the
error memory.
So,
you just request
related
to
2292,
and the answer
will be the amount
of,
among all the information
that are provided,
the amount
of cycles
left to
delete the error
from the
error memory.
Last thing
to say,
of course,
this is
the behavior
of the software
once we sell
the car.
So,
we sell the car
with all the
echo
and the echo
that we
validated.
So,
this is the
intended behavior
once the car
is out there.
Because,
as I said,
it's very important
to keep track
of the error
if I have
an error
on the
electronic
control.
If I had
an error
on the
accelerator pedal,
I would be
glad if the
echo knows
about it
and remembers
it.
So,
next time
I bring the
car to the
mechanics
for doing
some kind
of
maintenance,
it appears
that I have
any problem
with the
accelerator pedal.
So,
it won't
happen again.
Probably,
I don't know,
they will
replace it
anyway,
just in case
and stuff
like this.
So,
it's very
important
we have
to.
So,
this is
important
during the,
let's
say,
when we
sell
power.
But,
while we're
doing,
during the
development
phase,
of course,
if I have
to validate
the behavior
of a DTC,
and please
remember,
in the
powertrain
electronic
control unit,
we might
also have
300,
350,
400,
DTCs.
So,
just imagine
doing every
test that
you do,
every time
you have
to perform
monitoring
cycles,
warm-up
you know,
it will
take like
10 years
to validate
all the
DTCs
inside a
project.
So,
to simplify,
there are
many tricks,
let's say,
to simplify
the activities
of the
testers,
but the
main
trick,
let's say,
that is
always used,
is using
this specific
service,
which is
the
service 14,
that is used
to delete
the error
memory.
so you
just
launched
service 14
in a
specific way
and the
EEPROM
will get
deleted
about the
DTCs
stored inside
the electronic
quantum
environment.
In order
to delete
the EEPROM
about the
electronic
DTCs,
the service
to be sent
is the
14 with
the additional
3 bytes
FFFF.
So,
using
this
service,
services
and services,
then we
are going
to delete
all the
DTCs
inside
the electronic
quantum
load.
Of course,
if you
want
details
about
this
service,
everything
is
listed
and
explained
inside
the
EDS.
So,
I
suggest
you
to go
there
for
further
details.
But anyway,
it's very
important
that we
have
this
service
because
without
this
service,
every
time to
validate
the
DTC
will
take
years.
In
this
way,
once
I
realized
that
okay,
39,
38,
the
status
goes
to
08,
then
I
don't
know,
I
arrived
to
35,
then
I
requested
service
1906,
I
realized
that
it's
actually
35,
so
everything
is
working.
So,
once
you're
done,
okay,
I'm
sure
that
this
logic
is
working,
I
just
use
service
FFFF,
the
error
memory
will
get
deleted,
so
the
status
will
00.
Okay,
so
I
hope
this
clarifies
everything
related
to
going
back
to
the
status
00.
Of
course,
there
are
all the
information
inside
the
slides
and
inside
the
norm.
There
will
be
a
third
module
related
to
how
read
the
UDS
chapter.
They
are
all
the
same,
so
for
all
services
we
will
have
the
same
structure
of
the
chapter
and
with
that
third
module
then
you
will
have
everything
you
need
to
start
working
on
the
facilities
that
you
have
both
on
your
work
or
for
training
purposes
in
all
Kineton
offices.
In case
something
is not
clear,
some
improvements
are
needed,
there
are
some
kind
of
problems,
once
again,
you
can
write
to
pasquale.perrota
at
sign
kineton.it
or
automotive.training
at
sign
kineton.it